<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>India on Chitharanjan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://cdax.github.io/tags/india/</link>
    <description>Recent content in India on Chitharanjan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 00:41:34 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cdax.github.io/tags/india/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is the National Emergency of 1975 seen as one of the most controversial times in the History of India?</title>
      <link>https://cdax.github.io/post/1975-emergency/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 00:41:34 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cdax.github.io/post/1975-emergency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted as an answer to the question &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/History/Why-is-the-National-Emergency-of-1975-seen-as-one-of-the-most-controversial-times-in-the-History-of-India&#34;&gt;Why is the National Emergency of 1975 seen as one of the most controversial times in the History of India?&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/&#34;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll begin with your first question, &lt;strong&gt;the reasons&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two important developments leading up to the 1975 emergency, that can be credited with its imposition [1].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first of these, the JP Movement, initiated by students in Bihar and later lead by veteran political leader Jayaprakash Narayan (JP) was targeted against growing misgovernance and corruption under the Congress regime. JP&amp;rsquo;s call to &amp;lsquo;Total Revolution&amp;rsquo; [2], addressed to his predominantly youth following generated tremendous popular enthusiasm and pushed Indira Gandhi into a corner. The laurels of the 1971 Indo-Pakistan war were far behind her now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second, more immediate cause, was a ruling by the Allahabad High Court on 12 June, 1975 that effectively rendered her election to Parliament, null and void. She had been found guilty on 2 out of 14 counts of election malpractices leveled against her by Raj Narain, who had lost the Rae Bareilly seat to her in the said election.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the days that followed, the pressure to resign began to mount on Indira Gandhi from many quarters, even from within her own party. In an unexpected reaction, she decided to have the President Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed sign and approve an ordinance declaring a state of internal emergency with effect from the midnight of 25 June, 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to your second question, regarding the procedure, is a little more complicated. Back in those days, the Constitutional procedure and requirements for imposing an emergency were very different from what they are now. This is because once the emergency was uplifted and a new government was elected to the Centre in 1977, no time was wasted in amending the very provisions that had made it astonishingly simple for Indira Gandhi to impose and sustain a state of emergency since 1975. [3] For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is no longer possible to declare an emergency on grounds of &amp;lsquo;internal disturbance&amp;rsquo; as it was in 1975. This term was replaced with the much more specific &amp;lsquo;armed rebellion&amp;rsquo; by an amendment in 1978.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to this same amendment, the cabinet&amp;rsquo;s approval is now required before an emergency can be declared by the President. In 1975, Indira Gandhi acted swiftly to get the President&amp;rsquo;s approval and chose to inform her cabinet the next morning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A declaration of emergency was, prior to the 1978 amendment, immune to judicial review. Simply put, such a declaration could not be contested in a court of law!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1975, an emergency, once approved by Parliament, could be extended for as long as the cabinet deemed necessary. The 1978 amendment has made it imperative for the Parliament to review its approval periodically, once every six months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back then, while approving the declaration or continuity of an emergency, all that was required was a simple majority of the Parliament &amp;ndash; which is at least half of the members present and voting. Thousands of the Congress&amp;rsquo;s political opponents, including many MPs and the chief rival Jayaprakash Narayan, had already been arrested and sent to jail without trial as was allowed under Emergency provisions then. With their opposition missing from Parliament, the Congress found it easy to manage this rather simple majority. Understandably, the 1978 amendment made the terms of Parliamentary approval stricter by replacing the requirement of a simple majority with that of a &amp;lsquo;special&amp;rsquo; majority. This requires the approval of at least two-thrids of the members present and voting, as well as at least half of the total strength of the Parliament (which includes members who are not present).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now coming to your third question, that of upliftment. The exact reasons for why Indira Gandhi finally chose to end twenty months of Emergency rule, remain unknown and hence open to wide speculation. Ramachandra Guha&amp;rsquo;s book, India After Gandhi, quotes a few possible explanations for this. That she was confident of being elected back to power in the elections that would follow, that she was competing with the Pakistan President who had declared fresh elections in his own state, that she disliked being cut off from public contact following the emergency, and that she was hurt by criticism targeted at her by independent foreign observers who could not be dismissed off as enemies of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Chapters 21 (The Rivals) and 22 (Autumn of the Matriarch) from Ramachandra Guha&amp;rsquo;s excellent book, India After Gandhi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Bihar Movement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Indian Polity by M. Laxmikanth, for information regarding the Constitution&amp;rsquo;s Emergency provisions, and also the 44th Amendment Act of 1978.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What major issues did India have at the time of its independence that are now resolved?</title>
      <link>https://cdax.github.io/post/india-at-independence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2014 00:32:26 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cdax.github.io/post/india-at-independence/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted as an answer to the question &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/What-major-issues-did-India-have-at-the-time-of-its-independence-that-are-now-resolved&#34;&gt;What major issues did India have at the time of its independence that are now resolved?&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/&#34;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To describe a few that come to mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;resettlement-of-refugees&#34;&gt;Resettlement of refugees&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it became clear that Indian independence would come at the cost of partition, people who wished to be part of the Indian dominion migrated in heavy numbers from across the border, leaving their land and property behind in what was to become Pakistan. Much of this migration happened post-independence, and the new government was immediately faced with the challenge of resettling them. Along with a lot of hard work on the part of the administration, a couple of very innovative methods were employed to redistribute land among the refugees in a just and efficient manner (read about the &amp;lsquo;standard acre&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;graded cut&amp;rsquo;). Many of the thriving Punjabi-populated colonies in Delhi (Patel Nagar, Lajpat Nagar,&amp;hellip;) were set up during this time, as was the city of Faridabad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;integration-of-the-princely-states&#34;&gt;Integration of the Princely states&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be a massive understatement to say that the British left behind just 2 states, India and Pakistan, because in effect they were leaving the new government the mammoth task of integrating over 500 princely states into the union. Chiefly owing to the efforts of Sardar Patel and his secretary VP Menon, many of these states acceded without much need for persuasion, though a few are infamous for having given us trouble. One of these, Kashmir, continues to be a bone of contention to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;framing-a-constitution&#34;&gt;Framing a Constitution&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have often heard people say that the three years that it took to frame the Indian constitution is a mark of inefficiency on the part of the Constituent Assembly, when similar operations in other countries (e.g., Japan) were completed within months. What is overlooked here are two important facts. First, the constitution was drafted entirely by Indians, and was not dictated or handed down to us by another nation (e.g., again, Japan). This in itself should be considered an achievement. And then there&amp;rsquo;s the fact that the sheer diversity among the members of the Constituent Assembly naturally led to near-incessant debates. Looking back, it is hard to believe we managed to do it in just three years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, India achieved more in those first few years following independence, than some of the recent coalitions have managed in their five-year terms in office. And to think, all of this was accomplished against the backdrop of rioting, the Kashmir problem, and the task of conducting the first election in independent India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few other major examples that are to be found in the pages of our early post-independence history, chief among them being the Green Revolution. This period of history however, remains largely ignored and un-chronicled even by our own historians. Ramachandra Guha&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;India After Gandhi&amp;rdquo; would be a good starting point for anybody who&amp;rsquo;s interested.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is Ashoka Maurya given the title of &#39;Great&#39;?</title>
      <link>https://cdax.github.io/post/ashoka-the-great/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:27:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cdax.github.io/post/ashoka-the-great/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted as an answer to the question &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/Why-is-Ashoka-Maurya-given-the-title-of-Great&#34;&gt;Why is Ashoka Maurya given the title of &amp;lsquo;Great&amp;rsquo;?&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/&#34;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India under Ashoka, we witness the successful culmination of an ambitious first experiment in empire-building. Much has been written about the aggression and cruelty that marked his reign prior to his conversion to Buddhism, and how this conversion was to play a silent role in the subsequent decline of the Mauryan empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These contentious issues apart, my personal belief is that Ashoka should forever be remembered for trying to persuade his subjects to adopt Dhamma, a social ethic that tried to unite them by invoking virtues of tolerance and respect for human dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, Mauryan society had visible divisions based on caste, regional and ideological differences. Ever since its inception in the mid-second millenium BC, Caste had been (and continues to be) a permanent fixture of Indian society. A number of unorthodox new sects including Buddhism and Jainism that flourished under Mauryan rule, did not endorse the caste system. None of them managed to eradicate it however. On the other hand, they ended up inviting strong disapproval from communities practising Vedic Brahmanism, an early form of Hinduism that was prominent at the time. Moreover, the vast Mauryan empire consisted of a number of culturally disjoint regions, from the former Greek territories in the north-west, to Kalinga in the south-east.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was as a response to these differences that Ashoka formulated his policy of Dhamma, which professed among other things:
- an equal respect for the sects and a plea for practicing tolerance, as also to respect one&amp;rsquo;s elders
- the uselessness of ritual ceremonies and animal sacrifice
- the need for non-violent conquest by Dhamma, as opposed to conquest by war&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is another matter entirely that Ashoka received little success with the implementation of his policies. What matters is that unlike many rulers who came after him, he tried and that his attempt marks a rare effort in the direction of establishing unity in the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the manner in which he communicated these ideas to his subjects &amp;ndash; through a number of rock and pillar inscriptions that were read out to them by literate locals on his behalf &amp;ndash; was quite a direct form of public address which was rarely ever practiced after his death. For me, his greatness lies in the fact that using Dhamma, he tried to set an example for future generations of rulers. An example that, to this day remains largely ignored and forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What was pre-Aryan india like?</title>
      <link>https://cdax.github.io/post/pre-aryan-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:23:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cdax.github.io/post/pre-aryan-india/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted as an answer to the question &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/What-was-pre-Aryan-india-like&#34;&gt;What was pre-Aryan india like?&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/&#34;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your question called for looking at pre-Aryan India from the following multiple perspectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;habitation&#34;&gt;Habitation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mountain of evidence unearthed by archaeologists over the years shows us that India was certainly not uninhabited before the coming of the Indo-Aryan speaking people (the &amp;ldquo;Aryans&amp;rdquo;) in around 1,500 BC. In fact, a first wave of urbanization had already swept past north-western and western India, long before the Aryans started setting up towns and cities in the Ganges Plain. The people of the Indus Valley (Harappan) Civilization are remembered for an advanced sense of civic planning, a far-reaching trade network, and for being one of the largest civilizations of the time (2,600 to 1,800 BC). But even the Harappans appear many hundreds of years down the line if one is to look at a history of human habitation in India. The earliest sites date back to about 30,000-10,000 BC. These include the rock shelters at Bhimbetka in Madhya Pradesh and the Sanghao caves in Pakistan. Evidence of developing human settlements in the long interim between this early era (the Paleolithic) and the Harappans, lies dotted all over the subcontinent, ranging from Ghalegay in the Swat Valley to the Edakkal caves in Kerala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;geography&#34;&gt;Geography&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Aryans are known to have cleared vast patches of forest lands in the Ganges Plain in order to fuel their widespread agricultural enterprise, it is probable that this part of India would have been more densely forested in earlier times. However, the landscapes of India&amp;rsquo;s other major geographical features &amp;ndash; the Northern Mountains, the Peninsula and the Coasts &amp;ndash; are likely to have suffered minimal changes as a result of Aryan activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, jungles weren&amp;rsquo;t everywhere, but a lot of forest cover was indeed cleared by the Aryans before they ushered in the second wave of urbanization in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;society&#34;&gt;Society&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caste-based division of society has its earliest mention mostly in the Vedas which, along with other textual sources like the Puranas, the Ramayana and the Mahabharata, have been used by historians to draw a number of insights into Aryan social life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Indus Valley Civilization that came prior to the Aryans, is unlikely to have witnessed a perfectly egalitarian society. The elaborate city plans and construction projects seen at major Harappan sites, hint to the possibility that a significant labour force was involved. The control and management of this kind of labour would have served as a source of power and authority. Evidence of a system of social stratification as elaborate and well-established as Caste, is nevertheless absent before the arrival of the Aryans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;legacy&#34;&gt;Legacy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of cults and practices that originated in pre-Aryan India were adapted, re-adapted and exported to other cultures by subsequent settlers and are visible even today &amp;ndash; these include the deity Shiva, goddess worship and phallic worship, and possibly fire worship and sacrifice as well. However, I am yet to learn about entire tribes that have survived largely unchanged from that era.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Kasol Affair</title>
      <link>https://cdax.github.io/post/kasol/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 22:46:27 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cdax.github.io/post/kasol/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It’s been four months since my first trip to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kasol&#34;&gt;Kasol&lt;/a&gt;. Looking back, I don’t regret not having kept an account of how I spent my time there. There’s a certain infectious quality about the relaxed air at Kasol. Once you’re there, enjoy the cool weather, eat the good food, live at the cheap hotels and meet the strange people. Of course there’s a lot else to do, but keeping a journal of my adventures was never a priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, while listening to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3uTzfhqdcn8&#34;&gt;Altaf Raja classic&lt;/a&gt; at work today, I finally chose to put something down out of sheer nostalgia (they listen to a lot of Altaf Raja up in the hills of Himachal Pradesh). I don’t intend to write a guide for someone already planning to backpack up to Kasol; there are many reliable travel guides out there. However, I do hope to get someone curious about places they may have never known to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;getting-there&#34;&gt;Getting There&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not many trains dare to ply over the Himalayan terrain, but the small town of Bhuntar, being in proximity to popular tourist destinations like Kasol, Kullu and Manali, boasts the luxury of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bhuntar_Airport&#34;&gt;a domestic airport&lt;/a&gt;. The Bhuntar Airport, erected on the west bank of the Beas river, is quite a sight but recent withdrawal of services by debt-ridden carriers Air India and Kingfisher have meant that it has been in-operational for a while. Ground staff sit around killing their time, even while people in search of a public toilet relieve themselves in a hidden corner of the Airport complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a kilometer or two away from this airport however, is the fully-functional Bhuntar bus depot. Buses arrive from most major North Indian towns, and it’s a twelve-hour journey from New Delhi’s ISBT Kashmere Gate in particular. You can book a seat in one of the inimitable Volvo buses for anywhere between Rs. 700 to 1000. As a note of caution, be very careful when selecting your bus at Kashmere Gate. Never trust hawkers who will offer you a cheap price by splitting your journey into two bus rides — this will usually end up with you getting stranded in an unknown town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve reached Bhuntar, the first thing to do is to make sure you draw out enough cash to sustain your stay in Kasol because up in the Parvati Valley, banks, ATMs and the police do not exist. After that, hitch a bus to Kasol, which is still a good 30 kilometers off and get set for the bus ride of your life — the vehicle plies chillingly close to the edges of Manikaran Road, that winds its way around mountains. Each bend in the road offers its own thrills. It’s incredible how two buses heading in opposite directions on the same narrow strip with a bottomless fall on one side, still manage to breeze past each other quite peacefully. In the two and a half hours that it takes to get to Kasol, the bus usually makes no more than two stops at nondescript settlements along the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdax.github.io/img/kasol-growth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cannabis growing wild in Kasol&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally feel that if you’ve got the time and the legs for it, then trekking those 30 kilometers to Kasol is the best way to get there. The picturesque landscape is dotted with apple orchards and a variety of birds, and Kasol announces itself with a sudden overgrowth of wild Cannabis (called Bhang by the locals, just in case you want to ask someone where to find some).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;staying-there&#34;&gt;Staying There&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the bus finally dropped me off at Kasol, I wasn’t concerned about immediately finding a place to stay, but I took some time to walk around and soak in the sudden change in sights and sounds. On either side of the main road were restaurants, cafes and bakeries — many of them had their names written in Hebrew. Over the years, a lot of Israelis have made Kasol their home, and it’s not difficult to see why. I walked into one peculiar looking shack, attracted by the sound of music playing inside it, but all I found was a deserted kitchen and empty chairs and tables. An unattended laptop computer played songs in a loop from a playlist. This is how I found this place both nights during my stay in Kasol — deserted, with music playing on a computer and an empty kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an abundance of inns and cyber cafes, travel agencies and handicraft shops. At the cyber cafes, I saw tourists talking to their families and friends back home over Facebook and Skype. While the owners of shops greeted me with suspicious looks, almost every foreigner carried a telling smile on his/her face. In places, the air smelled of burnt grass, and you knew that these smiles came from perpetual bliss supplemented with good, cheap food. A small bridge passing over the river Parvati offered an unimaginably scenic spot for visitors to hang out and smoke together in peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdax.github.io/img/moondance-cafe-view.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The view from Moondance Cafe&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed at &lt;em&gt;Hotel Kasol Inn&lt;/em&gt;, which offered a decent room with a double bed for just Rs. 300 per night. However, that much money gives you just one sheet and one blanket with which you must face the cold air of the valley. So it’s a good idea to carry your own quilts or blankets. The inn-keeper, though he seemed to be charging an extra Rs. 100 off dating/married couples, was a friendly man. He offered us some of his prized hash at an alleged discount, even before we (my flatmate and I) had checked into our rooms — or perhaps that was a marketing tactic. Outside Kasol Inn, we met a man who had probably one day just decided to abandon his life in his home town or city, and settle in Kasol. He made a living as a tattoo artist who was also a part-time t-shirt print designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;eating-there&#34;&gt;Eating There&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had caught a cold on my way from Bhuntar to Kasol, so after checking in, I set about looking for some warm soup. I entered a small shack owned by two Sikkhimese women. Their only other patron at the time was a man who spoke in Spanish, entertained a stray dog and flirted off-handedly with the younger of the two women. I ordered half a bowl of Thukpa, and some Momos. All of this cost me just Rs. 30. Thukpa is Sikkimese noodle soup prepared with an array of chopped vegetables, served piping hot. It helped my cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning I walked over to Moondance Cafe, which is a local favourite. Laid out seductively on a rack in their bakery, I saw a range of breads and cakes. And then there were breads and cakes that came stuffed with, and covered in that unearthly God-sauce, Nutella. Nowhere else have I seen everyday food tailored so beautifully to delight hungry people. People at Kasol were observed to be a whole lot hungrier than is normal. From Moondance I had a baguette, a spanish omelette, a coffee and a muffin and the cashier had my bill made out for a little over Rs. 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only other place I ate at during my stay — three places in twenty four hours is the best I could manage — was Bhoj Restaurant. They boasted a Specials menu, great music and an ambience that was even more chilled out than outside. I chose to have some lasagna, which didn’t turn out as well as I’d imagined. There are quite a few other places that I missed out on, most notably the cleverly named Wunder Bar, Little Italy, and that deserted kitchen that seemed to have an acute shortage of staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-to-do-there&#34;&gt;What to do There&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard people like to trek and go white water rafting in and around Kasol. But when you’re short on time and forced to prioritize, choose the one most rewarding activity. Walk about, look around and take a hint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;getting-back&#34;&gt;Getting Back&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back from Kasol is easy thanks to the many travel agents in the area. If you try to pay them plastic money however, they’ll charge you an extra Rs. 100, stating that they’ll have to travel to the nearest bank, which lies 30 kilometers away. Book a ticket from Bhuntar’s bus depot to wherever you’re headed next, and to get to Bhuntar, stop any bus on its way there from Manikaran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdax.github.io/img/kasol-parvati.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Parvati River, flowing through Kasol&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m far from finished with Kasol. I’ll be back there a few more times later in life. To a land frozen in time, where people will still be grooving to the tunes of Altaf Raja.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>