<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>India on Chitharanjan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://cdax.me/tags/india/</link>
    <description>Recent content in India on Chitharanjan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016, Chitharanjan Das</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 00:41:34 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://cdax.me/tags/india/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is the National Emergency of 1975 seen as one of the most controversial times in the History of India?</title>
      <link>http://cdax.me/post/1975-emergency/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 00:41:34 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cdax.me/post/1975-emergency/</guid>
      <description>This was originally posted as an answer to the question Why is the National Emergency of 1975 seen as one of the most controversial times in the History of India? on Quora.
I&amp;rsquo;ll begin with your first question, the reasons.
There were two important developments leading up to the 1975 emergency, that can be credited with its imposition [1].
 The first of these, the JP Movement, initiated by students in Bihar and later lead by veteran political leader Jayaprakash Narayan (JP) was targeted against growing misgovernance and corruption under the Congress regime.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What major issues did India have at the time of its independence that are now resolved?</title>
      <link>http://cdax.me/post/india-at-independence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2014 00:32:26 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cdax.me/post/india-at-independence/</guid>
      <description>This was originally posted as an answer to the question What major issues did India have at the time of its independence that are now resolved? on Quora.
To describe a few that come to mind:
Resettlement of refugees When it became clear that Indian independence would come at the cost of partition, people who wished to be part of the Indian dominion migrated in heavy numbers from across the border, leaving their land and property behind in what was to become Pakistan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is Ashoka Maurya given the title of &#39;Great&#39;?</title>
      <link>http://cdax.me/post/ashoka-the-great/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:27:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cdax.me/post/ashoka-the-great/</guid>
      <description>This was originally posted as an answer to the question Why is Ashoka Maurya given the title of &amp;lsquo;Great&amp;rsquo;? on Quora.
In India under Ashoka, we witness the successful culmination of an ambitious first experiment in empire-building. Much has been written about the aggression and cruelty that marked his reign prior to his conversion to Buddhism, and how this conversion was to play a silent role in the subsequent decline of the Mauryan empire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What was pre-Aryan india like?</title>
      <link>http://cdax.me/post/pre-aryan-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:23:32 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cdax.me/post/pre-aryan-india/</guid>
      <description>This was originally posted as an answer to the question What was pre-Aryan india like? on Quora.
Your question called for looking at pre-Aryan India from the following multiple perspectives:
Habitation A mountain of evidence unearthed by archaeologists over the years shows us that India was certainly not uninhabited before the coming of the Indo-Aryan speaking people (the &amp;ldquo;Aryans&amp;rdquo;) in around 1,500 BC. In fact, a first wave of urbanization had already swept past north-western and western India, long before the Aryans started setting up towns and cities in the Ganges Plain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Kasol Affair</title>
      <link>http://cdax.me/post/kasol/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 22:46:27 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cdax.me/post/kasol/</guid>
      <description>It’s been four months since my first trip to Kasol. Looking back, I don’t regret not having kept an account of how I spent my time there. There’s a certain infectious quality about the relaxed air at Kasol. Once you’re there, enjoy the cool weather, eat the good food, live at the cheap hotels and meet the strange people. Of course there’s a lot else to do, but keeping a journal of my adventures was never a priority.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>